Guide to the Mrs. Edward S. Harkness Collection of Lady Hamilton
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Mrs. Edward S. Harkness collection of Lady Hamilton
1730-1812
GEN MSS 23
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.2
(12 boxes) + 1 broadside folder, 1 art storage item
9 bound volumes of music manuscripts mainly by Italian composers; letters written by Lady Hamilton, Horatio Nelson, and Sarah Nelson; 10 reproductions of paintings and engravings of Lady Hamilton; 9 bound volumes of printed music; and Lady Hamilton's music cabinet.
Harkness, Mary Emma Stillman, 1874-1950
Hamilton, Emma, Lady, 1765-1815
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mrs. Edward S. Harkness, 1931.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains various items relating to Lady Emma Hamilton, mistress of the British naval hero Admiral Horatio Nelson. Included are a number of bound volumes of printed and manuscript music, several letters among Lady Hamilton's family members, and reproductions of portraits of Lady Hamilton.
Mistresses -- England; Music (performing arts) -- Italy -- 18th century; Music (performing arts) -- Italy -- 19th century; Musical works; Hamilton, Emma, Lady, 1765-1815; Harkness, Mary Emma Stillman, 1874-1950; Nelson, Horatio Nelson, Viscount, 1758-1805
- Manuscript music, Series I
  - Volume I: (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Cantata A Dve Voci Composta da Benedetto Baldi Per Ordine di Sua Eccellenza Miledi Hamilton A 29. 7bre 1799. [129] p.
  - Volume II: (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Dodici Duetti Per Soprano, e Contralto Col Basso Del Sigr. D. Francesco Durante. In Napoli Presso Luigi Marescalchi. [127] p. Decorated titlepage. Background of titlepage only engraved.
  - Volume III: (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Duettino Il tuo destino ingrata Con Recitativo Del Sigr. Sebastiano Nasolini in Napoli presso Luigi Marescalchi [43] p. Decorated titlepage. Titlepage only engraved.
    Duetto Serio Vieni a regnare, e a vivere Con Recitative Del Sigr. D. Giuse. Gazzaniga In Napoli presso Luigi Mareschalchi. [60] p. Decorated titlepage.
    Duetto Serio Vanne par che men penoso Con Recitativo Del Sigr. D. Benedetto Neri Per divertimento di S. E. Miledi Hamilton. [47] p. Decorated titlepage.
    Notturno A due Canti, e Basso, del S. Maestro Martino da Bologna. [15] p.
    In S. Cecilia 1799 Nel Trionfo della Religione Parla deh Parla almeno Duetto Serio A Due Soprani Musica Del Sigr. D. Franco. Fiderici. [42] p.
  - Volume IV (Autograph signature on the inside cover: Lady Hamilton, London, 1801.): (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Lady Hamilton 1801 Vederti Sol Bramo Duetto Del Sigr. Ferdinando Per [Paer]: Vederti Sol bramo. [63] p.
    Lady Hamilton 1801 Il Tua destino ingrato Duettino Il tuo destino ingrato Del Sigr. Nasolini. [45] p.
    Della Morte di Cleopatra Duetta Serio Del Sigr. D. Pietro Guglielmi Ah questo amplesso o Cara. [71] p.
    Rondo con recvo. (Del Sigr. Giuseppe Gazzaniga:) Ah non lasciarmi no. [68] p.
  - Volume V: (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Libro Decimoquinto Raccolta di Canzonette, ed Arie Di varj Autori Per uso Di S. E. Miledi Hamilton. 2 p.l.
    N.l. Canzonette Con Chitarra Francese Per Uso Di Madamoiselle Hart In Napoli Luichesi. [11] p. Decorated titlepage.
    N.2. Sei Ariette Con accompagnamento Di Giuseppe Niccolini Dedicate A. S. E. Miledi Hamilton. [21] p. Decorated titlepage.
    N.3. So che un Sogno e la speranza. Cavatina. Con Viola Obbligata Di Giuseppe Niccolini Dedicata A. S. E. Miledy Hamilton. [11] p. Decorated titlepage.
    N.4. Canzoni ... Popolari cioe Alla Siciliana, alla Catanese. ed. alla Palermitana. [14] p.
    N.5. Canzona Greca N.5 Federico Fico, copi. [5] p.
    N.6. La Ninna Nonna N.6 Or che il silenzio Musica Del Sig. D. Giuseppe Millico Federico Fico, copista. [14] p.
    N.7. Dodeci Canzonette N.7 Con Accompagto. di Clavicembalo Del Sigr. Francesco Piticchio 1790. [48] p.
    N.8. Venzia 1791 Nel Oratorio, intitolato, Terico Diruta Ah! si vivit cor humanum - N. 8 reccvo. e Aria Del Sigr. Pasquale Anfossi. [38] p.
  - Volume VI: (Box 2, Folder 6)
    MS song: "Oh God, thy mercy shed on his Annointed Head ..." 2 l.
    Preghiera Nell Ines de Castro Del Sig. Francesco Bianchi. [17] p.
    Song beginning: "Pleas'd would I strike the lyre ..." Composed for Lady Hamilton. 1801, Dec. [7] p.
    Arianna a Naxos: Cantata Del Sigr. Giuseppe Haydn. [38] p.
    Via dite cosa avete Duetto Buffo Del Sigr. D. Giovanni Paisiello. [87] p.
    The Spirits Song and "She never told her love ..." Del Sigr. Giuseppe Haydn. [13] p.
    Duettino Deh tu conforta oh Cara Del Sigr. Domenico Cimarosa. [17] p.
    Canzoncina Nasco Nel vago Aprile Con Chittarra Del Sigr. Giuseppe Lanza. [17] p.
    Ariette per Voce di Soprano Con Accom- pagto. D. Arpa O Cembale Del Sigr. Giuseppe Millico. [31] p.
  - Volume VII: (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Terzetto nel Matrimonio Segretto Sento oi me che mi vien male Del Signore Domenico Cimarosa. [59] p.
    Song: "When menac'd a gallic usurper this shore ...", one voice with piano accompaniment. [7] p.
    Con Qvell' Occhietto Langvido Dvetto Del Sigr. Vinter. [10] p.
    Cantata In lode di Lord Nelson Composta Per il giorno Natalizio Di Lady Hamilton. [14] p.
    Brice vi diro sentite bene Del Signore D. Domenico Cimarosa. [31] p.
    Preghiera Ah ti muova oh Ciel pietoso Con Recitativo e Duettino Del Sigr. D. Giuse. Curci Nella Zulema In Napoli presso Luigi Marescalchi. [63] p.
    O Astra O Coelum Composed by William Beckford Esquire October 1800. [6] p.
    ... Recitativo & Duetto Con Violini, Oboe, corni Viole & Basso del Sig. Francesco Bianchi per uso della Signa. Marianna Arena. [29] p.
    Perdonate Signor mio; Nel Matrimonio Secreto Aria Buffa Con Violini, Oboe, Corni, Viole, Fagotto, e Basso Del Sigr. D. Domenico Cimarosa Della Siga. Teresa Saetana Torriggiani. [55] p.
  - Volume VIII: (Box 3, Folder 8)
    Libro Quinto Raccoltadi Terzetti Composti da varii Autori Per uso di S. E. Miledi Hamilton In Napoli. 1 l. Decorated titlepage.
    N.1. Tritto Terzetto: Perche se mia. [63] p.
    N.2. Antigono - S: Carlo 178 S? Terzetto 2 Deh mira nel mio pianto Musica Del Sigr. D. Giovanni Paisiello. [47] p.
    N.3. Enea e Lavinia Napoli nel Real Teatro di S. Carlo Preghiera Bella pace o mai discendi Musica Del Sigr. D. Pietro Guglielmi. [31] p.
    N.4. Enea e Lavinia Napoli nel Real Teatro di S. Carlo Terzetto 4 Resta o' cara e calma in tanto Musica Del Sigr. D. Pietro Guglielmi. [79] p.
    N.5. Nel Medonte Napoli nel Real Teatro di S. Carlo Terzetto 5 Termate empi tremati Musica Del Sigr. D. Giuseppe Sarti. [55] p.
    N.6. Terzetto Buffo 6 Diro che perfida che falsa sei Del Sigr. D. Vincenzo Martin Nella Cosa Rara In Napoli presso Luigi Marescalchi. [56] p. Decorated titlepage.
  - Volume IX: (Box 3, Folder 9)
    Chi ma' tolto poveretta Duetto Del Sigr. D. Valentino Fioravanti. [67] p. Decorated titlepage.
    La cosa non va netta Duetto Del Sigr. D. Giovanni Paisiello. [55] p.
    Resta in pace o mio tesor: Ronda Del Sigr. D. Giovanni Paisiello. [43] p.
    Canzonette, e Duettino Composte di Nicola Signorile per uso di S. E. Miledy Hamilton. [20] p. Decorated titlepage.
    Elfrida Recvo. con Duetto Abbracciami o sposo Musica Del Sigr. D. Giovanni Paisiello. [47] p.
    Duetto Serio Non mi parlar d'amore Con Recitativo Del Sigr. D. Giovanni Paisiello. [95] p.
    Due Canzonette e due Duettini Composte di Nicola Signorile, ed umilmente dedicate a S. E. Miledy Hamilton. [14] p. Decorated titlepage.
    Due Canzonette ed Un Duettino Composti di Niccolo Signorile ed Umilmente dedicate A. S. E. L'Ammiraglio Lord Nelson Duca di Bronte. [14] p. Decorated titlepage.
- Correspondence, Series II
  - Hamilton, Emma, Lady
    - ALS to Mrs. Russell, 1812 Dec (21?) (Box 3, Folder 10)
      Letter franked by William Beckford
  - Nelson, Horatio Nelson
    - ALS to Captain Devonshire, 1801 May 23 (Box 3, Folder 11)
      St. George
  - Nelson, Sarah
    - 21 ALS to Lady Emma Hamilton, 1801-05 (Box 3, Folder 12)
      Swassham, Canterbury and Hilborough
    - 2 ALS to Charlotte Nelson, her daughter, 1805 (Box 3, Folder 13)
      Canterbury
    - ALS to her son, Horatio, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 14)
      No place. Note following on page 3, from her husband, signed W. M.
- Other Papers, n.d.; Series III
  - Ten reproductions of paintings and engravings by Romney, Reynolds, etc. (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Lady Hamilton's music cabinet, n.d.
- Printed Music, Series IV
  Individual pieces also cataloged separately
  - Bound volume of printed music, ca. 1789-99 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    Includes works by: Ignaz Pleyel, Franz Kotzwara
  - Bound volume of printed music, ca. 1730-50 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    Includes works by: George Frideric Handel
  - Bound volume of printed music entitled "Abel, Schroeters &c. Sonatas", 1760-80 (Box 6, Folder 18)
    Includes works by: Johann Samuel Schroeter, Karl Friedrich Abel, Ferdinando Pellegrino, Ernst Eichner
  - Bound volume of printed music, 1770-97 (Box 7, Folder 19)
    Includes works by: Ignaz Pleyel, Mattia Vento, Leopold Kozeluch, Bonifazio Asioli, Michele Nasci
    Includes: 1 piece of manuscript music; Ouverture du Jeune Henry - musique de [Etienne Nicolas] Méhul - arrangée pour le forte-piano par l'auteur. [14] p.
  - Bound volume of printed music, 1790-1800 (Box 8, Folder 20)
    Includes works by: Padre Martini, Francesco Durante, Benedetto Marcello, Joseph William Holder, Johann Baptist Vanhal, Leopold Kozeluch
  - Bound volume of printed music, 1770 (Box 9, Folder 21)
    Includes works by: Johann Christian Bach
  - Bound volume of printed music, 1790-1800 (Box 10, Folder 22)
    Includes works by: Dorothea Phillips (Mrs. Francis) Plowden, Johann Georg Graeff, Giacomo Gotifredo Ferrari
  - Bound volume of printed music entitled "Vento's Sonatas Vol. I", 1770-79 (Box 11, Folder 23)
    Includes works by: Mattia Vento
  - Bound volume of printed music, 1765-75 (Box 12, Folder 24)